# **Naveed Fazili**

I hold a doctorate in biochemistry with 12 international publications to my credit. I am passionate about biological sciences and have taught biochemistry at the undergraduate level for two years. Overall, I have around four years of post Ph.D. work experience.



- 🔽 fazilinaveed5@gmail.com 🤳 +91-7889806745
- 🕋 H.No. 9A, Hillview colony east Sector I old airport road, 190005 Srinagar i June 9, 1984 📔 Indian
- in linkedin.com/in/naveedfazili

# **Education**

Jun 2011 - May 2015

Aug 2006 - Jul 2008

Mar 2003 - Jan 2006

**Academic distinction** 

Work experience

Dec 2022 - Present

Aug 2021 - Feb 2022

Nov 2020 - Dec 2020

Ph.D

Aligarh Muslim University, Aligarh

M.Sc

Aligarh Muslim University, Aligarh

B.Sc

**University of Kashmir** 

Secured 14th position across entire Kashmir division in High School examination conducted by JKBOSE in the year 2000.

#### Associate

**Hurix Digital** 

- Creating video solutions for a range of problems pertaining to different domains of biological sciences.
- Utilizing feedback from clients and colleagues to improve content quality.

### ERC DLS associate

**Amazon India** 

- Reviewed the medical documents of Amazon US employees relevant to their clinical conditions and disability scenarios.
- Assisted with day-to-day operations, working efficiently and productively with all team members.

#### Lecturer

**Department of Higher Education, J&K** 

- Taught various disciplines of biochemistry at the undergraduate level by using state-of-the-art teaching aids.
- Toured my students to the established biochemistry labs in different colleges.

## Apr 2018 - Jul 2019

#### Lecturer

# **Department of Higher Education, J&K**

- Mentored and taught undergraduate students the theoretical and practical aspects of cell biology, immunology, and enzymology.
- Conducted individual sessions with the students to guide them about future career and job-related opportunities.
- Used PowerPoint and Google Classroom technology to give presentations to student classrooms.

#### Sep 2017 - Apr 2018

#### Lecturer

#### **SKUAST-Kashmir**

- Taught biochemistry at the undergraduate and postgraduate levels.
- Applied innovative teaching methods to encourage student learning objectives.

#### May 2016 - Dec 2016

#### Post-Doctoral Fellow

#### **IIT-Kanpur**

- Worked in the field of protein fibrillation and amyloidosis with a special focus on therapeutic interventions for amyotrophic lateral sclerosis.
- Moreover, I also assisted doctoral students in the domain of amino acid selfassembly, especially phenylalanine self-assembly which is relevant to the pathogenesis of phenylketonuria.

# Skills

## **Proofreading**

## **Microsoft Office**

**Content writing** 

## **Bioinformatics**

# **Grants**

- Received National Post-doctoral fellowship (N-PDF) from DST-SERB on March 10, 2016 under the scheme no. PDF/2015/000696.
- Received Travel grant from SERB-DST to attend an international conference in Paris, France in December 2014 under the sanction no. SB/ITS-Y/04560/2014-2015.
- Received Senior-research fellowship (SRF) from Indian council of medical research (ICMR) for a period of one year bearing the award no. 45/03/2014-BIO/BMS.

## **Certifications**

EF Standard English Test (EF SET): **B2 Upper Intermediate** 

Microsoft Powerpoint 2013 via LinkedIn

#### **Publications**

- 1. Furkan M, **Fazili NA**, Afsar M, Naeem A (2016) Analyzing cytochrome c aggregation and fibrillation upon interaction with acetonitrile: An in vitro study. Journal of Fluorescence 26:1959–1966.
- 2. **Fazili NA,** Naeem A (2016) Exploring the transition of human  $\alpha$ -Synuclein from native to the fibrillar state: Insights into the pathogenesis of Parkinson's disease. Journal of Fluorescence 25: 1659–1669.

- 3. **Fazili NA,** Bhat IA, Bhat WF, Naeem A (2015) Anti-fibrillation propensity of a flavonoid baicalein against the fibrils of HEWL: Potential therapeutics for lysozyme amyloidosis. Journal of Biomolecular structure and Dynamics 10: 1–45.
- 4. Naeem A, Khan TA, **Fazili NA** (2015) Protein folding and misfolding: A perspective from theory. Journal of Glycomics and Lipidomics 5:1.
- 5. **Fazili NA,** Siddiqui GA, Bhat SA, Afsar M, Furkan M, Naeem A (2015) Rifampicin induced aggregation of Ovalbumin: Malicious behavior of antibiotics. Protein Peptide Letters 22: 644–653.
- 6. **Fazili NA**, Naeem A, Ashraf GM, SH G, Kamal MA (2015) Therapeutic interventions for the suppression of Alzheimer's disease: Quest for a remedy. Current Drug Metabolism 16: 346–353.
- 7. **Fazili NA,** Naeem A (2014) Anti-fibrillation potency of caffeic acid against an antidepressant induced fibrillogenesis of human  $\alpha$ -synuclein: Implications for Parkinson's disease. Biochimie 108: 178–185.
- 8. **Fazili NA,** Ahmad M (2014) In vitro analysis of the phytotoxic and genotoxic potential of Aligarh wastewater and Mathura refinery wastewater. Toxicology Reports 1: 981–986.
- Amani S, Nasim F, Khan TA, Fazili NA, Furkan M, Bhat IA, Khan JM, Khan RH, Naeem A (2014) Detergent induces the formation of IgG aggregates: A multimethodological approach. Spectrochimica Acta Part A: Molecular and Biomolecular Spectroscopy 120: 151–160.
- 10. **Fazili NA**, Bhat WF, Naeem A (2014) Induction of amyloidogenicity in wild type HEWL by a di- aldehyde: Analysis involving multi-dimensional approach. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules 64: 36–44.
- 11. **Fazili NA,** Naeem A (2013) In vitro hyperglycemic condition facilitated the aggregation of lysozyme via the passage through a molten globule state. Cell Biochemistry and Biophysics 66: 265–275.
- 12. Naeem A, **Fazili NA** (2011) Defective protein folding and aggregation as the basis of neurodegenerative diseases: The darker aspect of proteins. Cell Biochemistry and Biophysics 61: 237–250.

# **Conferences and workshops**

- Participated in an international conference on Nanotechnology & STEM-ER under the title "Aligarh Nano-V & STEMCON-16" organized by the Centre of excellence in materials science (Nanomaterials), AMU, Aligarh from March 12-15, 2016.
- Presented a poster in an international conference on "Emerging Trends in Biomedical Sciences" organized by the Department of Biochemistry, Faculty of Life sciences, Aligarh Muslim University, Aligarh, India from March 6-8, 2016.
- Presented a poster in a national seminar "Clinical Chemistry Update" organized by the Department of Clinical Biochemistry, Sher-I-Kashmir Institute of Medical Sciences (SKIMS), Srinagar under the aegis of Association of clinical Biochemists of India (ACBI) on August 25, 2015.
- Attended a science communication workshop organized by Welcome trust-DBT alliance which was held on March 26, 2015 at Aligarh Muslim University, Aligarh, India.
- Presented a paper in a National symposium on "Recent advances in free radical biology and biochemistry" organized by the Department of Biochemistry, Faculty of Life sciences, Aligarh Muslim University, Aligarh, India on March 6, 2014.

# **References**

- Dr. Aabgeena Naeem from Department of Biochemistry AMU, Aligarh aabgeenanaim@gmail.com; aabgeenanaim@rediffmail.com
- Prof. Khalid Majid Fazili from D/o Biotechnology, University of kashmir, J&K fazili@kashmiruniversity.ac.in